Finding Aid for the Cyrus Daniel Papers
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
Cyrus Daniel Papers
1937-1967
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
MSS.0099
1.26 linear_feet
Biography
Cyrus Daniel was born on February 27, 1900. He received an A.B. in Greek from Shurtleff College in Alton, Illinois, and a Mus. B. in Organ and Composition from Northwestern University. He taught for a year in New Trier High School in Winnetka, Illinois. He held the position of Professor of Theory and Composition at Lawrence Conservatory in Appleton, Wisconsin until September 1944. He came to Vanderbilt University in 1944 as a Visiting Lecturer in Music and Music Literature and remained as a Lecturer in Music and as University Organist until 1968. After the planting of the Centennial Oak (Saturday, March 17, 1973) in celebration of the Vanderbilt University Centennial, the first performance of “Golden Morning” – composed by Cyrus Daniel was heard by the carillon. Mr. Daniel composed the music as a setting for the Donald Davidson lyric poem about the Vanderbilt campus.
Scope and Content Note
The Cyrus Daniel Papers include compositions and arrangements by Daniel; miscellaneous programs 1944-1951; a bound copy of Vanderbilt University A Cappella Choir History, 1937-1967; and a selection of A Cappella Choir records, 1944-1965.
- Programs (1944-1951) – Peabody concerts, Vanderbilt choir concerts, Vanderbilt commencement Sundays, Sunday recital series, Vanderbilt Theater (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Vanderbilt University – A Cappella Choir History, 1937-1967 – a bound volume of correspondence, contributors, programs, photographs, clippings (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Op.3 “Sketches in Romantic Style for Piano”, No. 1 Autumn – dedicated to Ruth (Mrs. Dawson) Saug, Hobe Sound, Florida, a “breath of the South” in Appleton, Wisconsin No. 2 April – dedicated to Dr. Beverly Douglas, Nashville, Tennessee, plastic surgeon, inventor, and tenor soloist. Cyrus Daniel an honorary Alumnus of his class in Princeton No. 3 Lora – dedicated to Lora (Mrs. Oscar) Reinke, Neenah, Wisconsin, and artist and devoted friend (Box 1, Folder 3)
- “Sonata No. 1 for Pianoforte” (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Op. 10 1943 “Sonata No. 2 for B Minor in Piano” – dedicated to Professor Arne Oldberg, Evanston, Illinois (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Op. 21 No. 1 “College Songs” (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Op. 21 No. 2 “College Songs” No. 2 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Op. 21 No. 3 “College Songs” No. 3 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Op. 21 No. 4 “College Songs” No. 4 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Op. 21 No. 5 “Songs of the Civil War” (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Miscellaneous, Op. 1 No. 2 “Nirvana” – (Wheeler) Dedicated to Dr. Carl Beecher, Evanston, Illinois Op. 1 No. 1 “Music, when soft voices die” – (Shelley) Dedicated to Dr. Marshall Hulbert, Appleton, Wisconsin Op. 2 No. 1 “Etude for Piano” – Dedicated to Cyrus Daniel’s eldest sister, Nora Ann Daniel, Upland, California Op. 2 No. 2 “Intermezzo” for Piano – Dedicated to Cyrus Daniel’s sister, Harriet Frances Daniel, Upland California Op. 11 No. 1 “Mit Freuden Zart” an organ processional – dedicated to Margaret (Mrs. Neil) Wright Op. 16 A “The Magnificat” – dedicated to Mrs. Lawrence (Larry) LaCour, a harpist (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Op. 15 “Remember Now Thy Creator” (12 copies) for male chorus and piano – written for Vanderbilt Men’s Glee Club, and performed with Cal Turner and John Wagner as soloists, and Helen Midkiff pianist the following year. Dedicated to Cyrus Daniel’s father, Chisley Daniel, Alton, Illinois, Op. 16 “The Christ Child in Prophecy and Fulfillment” (3 folders) – a short cantata for chorus, soloist and organ, with flute and hard obbligati. (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Op. 16 “The Christ Child in Prophecy and Fulfillment” (3 copies) Flute and Harp (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Op. 16 “The Christ Child in Prophecy and Fulfillment” Part I & II (5 copies) (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Op. 16 “The Christ Child in Prophecy and Fulfillment” Part I & II (7 copies) (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Op. 18 No. 1 “God is a Spirit” (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Op. 18 No. 2 “As it began to Dawn” (12 copies) – an Easter anthem dedicated to Edith (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Op. 14 “Psalm 68” (5 folders) A festival cantata for chorus, soloist and organ – Composed for the dedication of the new sanctuary of the First Presbyterian Church, Nashville, Tennessee, where Cyrus Daniel was the organist and choir director of music, and first performed there Thanksgiving, 1957. Op. 14 A, The Prelude, and Op. 14 B, “Let God Arise”
- Op. 14 “Psalm 68” – “Let God Arise” (13 copies) (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Op. 14 “Psalm 68” – “Sing Unto God” (13 copies) (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Op. 14 “Psalm 68” – “The Lord Gave the Word” (12 copies) (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Op. 14 “Psalm 68” – “Procession” (12 copies) (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Op. 14 “Psalm 68” – Miscellaneous, “Sing unto God”- Ladies Trio 5 copies, “A Father to the Fatherless” 2 copies, “A Command to God” 2 copies, “The Glory of God in the Sanctuary” (2 copies) (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Op. 12 1951 “A Biblical Trilogy” (12 copies) – for mixed voices, a capella, 3 choruses, subtitled: (Box 3, Folder 6)
  Comely, Wise and Wonderful
  The Winter is Past
  To Everything is a Season
  An alternate version with accompaniment by Woodwind quartet (oboe, clarinet, Horn and bassoon) was written in 1970. Subtitled simply to Nature, Love and Philosophy, it was performed in part at the University of South Florida, Tampa, in January 1971 Dedicated to Dr. Carl Waterman, long time Dean of the Lawrence Conservatory of Music, Appleton, Wisconsin
- Op. 17 “The Song is Mine” a suite for unaccompanied voices in five movements – the poem was written by Matilda (Mrs. John) Duke of Nashville, Tennessee, plus an added stanza by Cyrus Daniel to make a Scherzo possible. The movements are subtitled as follows:, Prelude – Evening Shadows Scherzo – Bright Stars Lament – Winter’s Mist Air and Finale – The Scarf of Spring Epilog – The Song is Mine (Box 3, Folder 7)